Albert A. D'Amico Papers VHP2006/30
CCSU Veterans History Project
Albert A. D'Amico Papers
Bulk, 1943-1946
1943 - 1946, 2006
VHP2006/30
CCSU Veterans History Project
79.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
This collection details of Albert A. D'Amico's World War II experience. He served as a Machinist Mate in the U.S. Navy in the Pacific. The collection contains personal letter, ship log, photographs, and video oral history interview.
D'Amico, Albert A., (Albert Anthony), 1923 - 2007
Biographical/Historical note
Albert D'Amico was drafted into the U.S. Army in 1943, but because he was too thin, they would not accept him, and sent him back home to New Britain, Ct. However, he found that the Navy would accept him, and he joined in April of 1943, weighing only 105-110 lbs. He went to boot camp in Sampson, NY, and transferred to an amphibious base in the Soloman Islands, MD. He trained on LST (Landing Ship Tanks) boats, where he learned mechanical work, including working in the main engine room and repairing diesel engines. Because D'Amico had been a machinist before joining the Navy, he was volunteered to run a smaller boat, an LCVP (landing craft vehicle personnel), which was housed in the larger LST, but was more efficient in transporting troops (36 soldiers per boat) to the shores. D'Amico was stationed on LST 278, which travelled through the Panama Canal to the Pacific Ocean, and finally landed in San Diego, where the men trained with the 2nd marine division. The sailors went on to Saipan, and began "island hopping", going from island to island, and transporting soldiers to the areas. He was awarded five battle stars, and was part of five major battles in the South Pacific. The first was the Battle of Saipan; the second was the Battle of Tinian just 30 days after the Battle of Saipan. From there, the sailors on LST 278 went to the Island of Peleliu. During the battle there the LST was repeatedly shot at, but it was the typhoon that hit them that finally sunk the ship. D'Amico was then sent to Pearl Harbor, Hawaii, for underwater demolition training. While there he found that his hearing and ear were damaged from the previous battles he had been a part of, and he was unable to complete the training. He was then transferred to LST 399, where he remained for the rest of the war. He was discharged in Long Island, NY in January of 1946, and returned home to New Britain, CT where he married, and had five children. He worked at New Britain Machine, and then Pratt and Whitney, until 1983. Alfred D'Amico passed away in December of 2007.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
LST 278 (Ship).; LST 399 (Ship) .; United States. Navy.; Iwo Jima, Battle of, Japan, 1945; Kamikaze; Okinawa-shi (Japan); Pearl Harbor (Hawaii); Peleliu Island (Palau); Peleliu, Battle of, Palau, 1944; Rosenthal, Joe, 1911-2006; Saipan; Saipan, Battle of, Northern Mariana Islands, 1944; Sampson Naval Training Station (Sampson, N.Y.); Solomons (Md.); Subic Bay (Philippines); Tinian (Northern Mariana Islands); United States. Navy--Machinist's mates; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Japan -- Okinawa Island; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Pacific Area; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American
- Series I: Personal Papers, VHP2006/30.I
  - Personal note to Albert D'Amico from his wife, May 1, 1995; VHP2006/30.I.1
  - Albert D’Amico’s Autobiography, n.d.; VHP2006/30.I.2
  - Interview synopsis, Nov. 27, 2006; VHP2006/30.I.3
- Series II: Military Documents, VHP2006/30.II
  - Reproduction of LST 278 Deck Log Book, Oct. 22, 1943; VHP2006/30.II.1
  - Reproduction of LST 399 Deck Logs, Jan. 1, 1944; VHP2006/30.II.2
- Series III: Publications, VHP2006/30.III
  - "Memorial donation" - New Britain Herald, May 3, 1996; VHP2006/30.III.1
  - Iwo Jima Survivors Association 10th Reunion Program, Aug. 17, 1997; VHP2006/30.III.2
  - Never in Doubt: Remembering Iwo Jima - book excerpt, 1999; VHP2006/30.III.3; 6.0 Digital objects
  - Memories of LST 399 - LST SCUTTLEBUTT Newsletter, November 2001; VHP2006/30.III.4
  - LST Reminiscence of a Motor Mac, circa 2001; VHP2006/30.III.5
  - Iwo Jima Survivors Journal, March 2003; VHP2006/30.III.6; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Certificate of Appreciation, May 29,2004; VHP2006/30.III.7
  - Drawing of LST 399, n.d.; VHP2006/30.III.8
  - The Iwo Jima Survivors of Connecticut, n.d.; VHP2006/30.III.9
  - "Cover commemorates Iwo Jima flag raising", n.d.; VHP2006/30.III.10
  - Cover jacket of VHS version "to the Shores of Iwo Jima" war film, n.d.; VHP2006/30.III.11; 2.0 Digital objects
- Series IV: Multi-Media, VHP2006/30.IV
  - Subseries A: Still images, VHP2006/30.IV
    - Civilian Conservation Corps Photo, 1941; VHP2006/30.IV.1; 2.0 Digital objects
    - Albert D’Amico (2nd row, 3rd from left) at boot camp. New York State, 1944; VHP2006/30.IV.2
    - Albert D’Amico and buddies at Club Baly, New Orleans, 1944; VHP2006/30.IV.3; 2.0 Digital objects
    - Three sailors posted with a donkey. Tijuana, Mexico, 1943; VHP2006/30.IV.4
      Scope and Contents note
      L - R: Prebee, Albert D’Amico, Jon. Taken at a stone front shop where they had a donkey on display, Tijuana, Mexico, 1944
    - Sailors posted at a stone front shop with a donkey on display. Tijuana, Mexico, 1943; VHP2006/30.IV.5
      L - R: George Lewin (Seaman), Albert D’Amico (MoMM 3/C), Lt. Martin Rosene, & Boats Mate Law
    - crews of LST 399 on liberty, San Francisco, CA, 1943; VHP2006/30.IV.6
    - Crew's quarters on LST 278, leaving San Francisco, CA for Pearl Harbor, HI, 1943; VHP2006/30.IV.7
      Albert D’Amico 4th from left in top row
    - Albert D’Amico at underwater demolition training, Maui, HI, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.8
    - Japanese cargo ship sunk by U.S. Navy at Iron Bottom Canal, Guadalcanal, 1944; VHP2006/30.IV.9
    - Albert D’Amico (top left) & crew members on LST 278. Peleliu, 1944; VHP2006/30.IV.10
    - Black Gang Crew from LST 278 at Battle of Peleliu, 1944; VHP2006/30.IV.11
      Albert D’Amico kneeling in center
    - LST 278 on Peleliu, before being sunk., Mar. 18, 1944; VHP2006/30.IV.12
    - Iwo Jima Beach at Battle Green Beach taken from the deck of LST 399, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.13
    - LST 399 on way to Battle of Iwo Jima, Mar. 19, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.14
    - D-Day going into Iwo Jima from LST 399, Mar. 19, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.15
      Albert D’Amico and Norman Marshall on boat #1
    - LST 399 with bow door and ramp open. Green Beach, Iwo Jima, Mar. 19, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.16
      Albert D’Amico on main deck upper left hand corner, crew mates below
    - LSTs beached and unloading equipments. Green Beach, Iwo Jima, Mar. 19, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.17
    - LSTs unloading supplies on Iwo Jima, Mar. 20, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.18
    - Green Beach at Battle of Iwo Jima taken from deck of LST 399, Mar. 20, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.19
    - Raising 2nd U.S. flag on Iwo Jima, Mar. 19, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.20
      Photo given to Albert D’Amico by Joe Rosenthal (photographer)
    - Japanese shrine on Ie Shima island, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.21
    - American cemetery on Ie Shima island, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.22
    - Ernie Pyle’s Grave, Ie Shima island, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.23
    - Wanna, Albert D’Amico’s Japanese wife by proxy, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.24
      All the English she knew was “me wife, you husband.” Albert D’Amico was taking her home to the Island of IE Shima about 5 miles from Okinawa in his small boat.
    - Albert D'Amico, his proxy wife, Wanna, and her family on the ramp of landing craft, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.25
      Albert D’Amico’s landing craft boat L - R:, Albert D’Amico, Wanna, Norman Marshall, She-Shee Wanna’s sister, Wanna’s brother on beach They are standing on the ramp of Albert D’Amicos boat “Glamour G.” IE Shima Island off Okinawa
    - LST 278's Black Gang Crew. Okinawa, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.26
      Albert D’Amico is in top left
    - Bunk inspection on LST 399 while off Okinawa, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.27
    - Bunk inspection on LST 399, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.28
    - Boat #1 for LST 809. Naha, Okinawa, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.29
    - American graves on Okinawa, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.30
    - Topside of LST 399 where Marine trucks were secured to main deck. Naha Beach, Okinawa, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.31
    - Crew’s quarters on LST 399, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.32
    - LSTs unloading equipment. Naha Beach, Okinawa, Apr. 1, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.33
    - Main deck of LST 399 loaded, going to beach Okinawa, Apr. 4, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.34
    - Japanese plane landed to surrender, Tinian, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.35
    - Japanese surrender to General McArthur, Tinian, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.36
    - Japanese surrender, Tinian, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.37
    - Japanese surrender, Tinian, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.38
    - Japanese plane lands to surrender, Tinian, 1945; VHP2006/30.IV.39
    - Charles Adnizio(LST 298), Mayor of Boston [John F. Collins -?], Albert D’Amico(LST278, 399) Boston Harbor, MA, 1990; VHP2006/30.IV.40
    - Albert D’Amico at Iwo Jima memorial in Washington, D.C., 1992; VHP2006/30.IV.41
    - Iwo Jima survivors meeting at New Britain Iwo Jima memorial site before memorial was erected. New Britain, CT, 1994; VHP2006/30.IV.42
    - Tour of company where they sculpted the Iwo Jima Memorial before display. New Jersey, 1994; VHP2006/30.IV.43
    - Iwo Jima survivors after parade in New Britain, CT, 1994; VHP2006/30.IV.44
    - Albert D’Amico at Iwo Jima memorial site. New Britain, CT, 1995; VHP2006/30.IV.45
    - Albert D’Amico’s stone marker on Iwo Jima Memorial. New Britain, CT, 1995; VHP2006/30.IV.46
    - Iwo Jima Memorial at night. New Britain, CT, 1995; VHP2006/30.IV.47
    - Carrying flag during Memorial Day Parade. Westport, CT, 1995; VHP2006/30.IV.48
    - Albert and his wife Jeanette D’Amico at LST Convention. Washington D.C., 1995; VHP2006/30.IV.49
  - Subseries B: Moving images, VHP2006/30.IVb
    - Oral history interview with Albert D'Amico, Nov. 27, 2006; VHP2006/30.IVb.1; Hurst, Eileen (Disk DVD VHP2006/30, Box VHP Interview 2006)